# Gaurav Bajaj

## **Senior Software Engineer**

Mobile no.: +91-8380889772/7070461757

LinkedIn-id: https://www.linkedin.com/in/bajaj-gaurav/ Git link: https://github.com/bajaj-gaurav

## **PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE** (6+ years)

### **VMware Software India** (Senior Software Engineer)

(Dec 2017 - Current)

Email: bajajgaurav86@gmail.com

Responsible for creating scalable, reliable and maintainable cloud native services. The work requires an Expertise in System Design, Understanding of Cloud Infrastructure like AWS, Programming Expertise, Operational Experience, Knowledge on Logging and Monitoring, Following Best Practices of Agile Methodologies, Problemsolving skills at Scale, Designing, Building and Operating Fault-Tolerant, Scalable and Distributed Software and Web applications.

#### **Core Responsibilities:**

- Experienced in end-to-end software development in the cloud, including **Designing**, **Developing**, Deploying and Supporting systems. Been involved in entire software development lifecycle from understanding requirements to supporting the deployed system.
- Worked towards improving the **Stability**, **Performance Metrics** and **Handling Scale** of the service.
- Implemented the best practices of Monitoring & Observability (monitoring, logging, and tracing) to make our product more resilient to failures.
- Worked on R&D projects like Building Recommendation Engine using ML & AI technologies which focused on reducing operational burden by Automated Recommendation and Remediation.
- Lead R&D projects like Building Q&A Portal which aimed at providing correct information from various internal documentation sources quickly. Basically, it is a 1 click solution to find relevant information.
- Designed, Developed and Deployed Microservices/RESTful services on the cloud.
- Designed & implemented Backend RESTful APIs.
- Used Git, Jenkins, Docker and Kubernetes for Continuous Integration, Development and Deployment.
- Used **AWS** as the cloud solution and experienced in **Database** design and implementation.
- Used Java and Spring boot for developing the platforms with Best Practices of Coding.
- Built services to Visualize Availability and Reliability data points.
- Mentored, trained and guided junior members in the team.

#### **Calsoft Inc.** (Software Developer)

(July 2016 - Nov 2017)

#### Overview:

Worked as an Engineer to automate the configuration for creating large datacenters. Worked in the RnD team to explore new emerging technologies and provide company-wide training to build the knowledge base in the company which could bring in more projects to the company. Inculcated more automation in the practices of the company.

## **Core Responsibilities:**

- Written custom python modules and playbooks in Ansible as a part of the project which relies heavily on automation of networking 12/13 environment
- Changed the **open-source code of Ansible** as per the use case of the project which required customization in callback plugin, connection plugin, etc.
- RnD/training on technologies: Ansible, Chef, Puppet, ELK, Cobbler, Vagrant and Docker

## **Dextorous Services** (Web Development Lead)

(June 2015 - Feb 2016)

#### Overview:

Worked as a lead software developer to develop and deliver an eCommerce platform. The work required sound knowledge of designing and developing services within a quick span of time. The work also included Interacting and Getting the requirements from the Client, Managing the team, and Delivering requirements.

#### Core Responsibilities:

- Implemented and Integrated Reviews and Ratings feature within the web platform.
- Written scripts for crawling data from most of the educational websites (like shiksha.com, indiacollegesearch.com, etc.) after which the data was processed and stored in the database for the retrieval
- Integrated the Search Functionality.
- Implemented and integrated **Blogging Platform** within the website to get more **Traffic.**

## PROJECTS (https://github.com/bajaj-gaurav)

#### 1. Title: Numerical TicTacToe

• Developed the game Numerical TicTacToe using **Reinforcement Learning** where the system is able to play the game with another player with a very high win ratio.

#### 2. Title: Chatbot

- Developed a **chatbot** that can chat with the customer and give the optimal search result.
- It uses Natural Language Processing (NLP) to process and understand words.
- Used Rasa framework to develop the chatbot

# 3. Title: Hand-based Image Gesture Recognition

- Given a sequence of hand-based gestures, the tech was able to recognize the action which we are trying to do.
- The tech had the core which was built using **Neural Networks**

## 4. Title: Prayaas

• Website which aimed to help spread the reach of the social organization called Prayaas.

## RESEARCH PROJECT

#### 5. Title: Openstack Cloud

The project was done to build a capability where-in the administrator could provide **compute resources** on-need basis to the students for their RnD purposes. Openstack was chosen to build the required infrastructure. Configured **IAAS service in cloud(private)** with autoscaling. It provided functionalities similar to AWS AMAZON where a person can create instances and use resources as per requirements with extra features like load balancing and automatic orchestration.

**Institute: VNIT NAGPUR** 

#### **EDUCATION**

- PG Diploma in Machine Learning (ML) and Artificial Intelligence (AI) from IIIT, Bangalore
- B. Tech degree in Computer Science & Engineering from Visvesvaraya National Institute of Technology, Nagpur

#### **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

- Programming languages and Web development framework: Java, Python, Spring boot, Flask
- Architecture: Microservice, Distributed System, Cloud Native Services, RESTful Services, MVC
- DevOps: Git, Ansible, Jenkins, Solr, Docker, Kubernetes, Terraform, Kibana, Wavefront, Logz
- Incident Management: Jira, Confluence
- Machine Learning (ML) & Artificial Intelligence (AI), Data Analytics
- Other: AWS, Database design, Data Structures, Algorithms, Software Design, OOPs, Cloud, Queueing, Kafka, Postman, Locust, Junit, SQL, Mentoring, BigPanda, System Design, API Development, Data Engineering
- Testing: Unit testing, Functional testing, Integration testing, Performance testing, End to End testing(E2E)
- System Architecture, Software Development, Automation, Web Application Development, Agile Methodologies

#### **ACHIEVEMENTS AND HONOURS**

- Spot Awards in VMware (for the leadership skills)
- Appreciation for exceptional mentorship at VMware
- Best new-comer award at Calsoft (for the work excellence)
- Best mentor award at Calsoft (mentoring B.E. students and having the best outcome)
- Recognition for CSR activities (part of teaching community)
- Chess Champion at Calsoft
- Selected as an official mentor to guide the newcomers in the VNIT College, Nagpur
- Member of the core team for organizing national social entrepreneurship conference, RENAISSANCE 2016

# **PERSONAL TRAITS**

- Strongly believe in Making Long-term Impact with a Futuristic Vision, Taking Full Ownership, Having Deep Knowledge & Understanding Concepts in Depth, Innovating and Delivering Results
- Ability to Produce results in Pressure situations
- Hard-working, Adaptable, Good Team Player
- Quick-Learner and Recognized Problem-Solving skills